<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-30T11:24:11-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jessy Leigh Gervais</title><author><name>Jessy Leight Gervais</name><email>jl@copykit.io</email></author><entry><title type="html">TileForge</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/tileforge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TileForge" /><published>2023-06-29T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-06-29T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/tileforge</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/tileforge/"><![CDATA[<p>TileForge is a dynamic, user-friendly, online map builder designed for tabletop role-playing games. A free-to-use tool, it empowers users to draw and embellish intricate maps, like a medieval castle, a bustling tavern, or an enchanted forest. This tool is a perfect companion to Virtual Tabletops (VTTs like Roll20), allowing users to create and play immersive tabletop role-playing games virtually.</p>

<p>You can try the builder out at: <a href="https://app.tileforge.com">app.tileforge.com</a></p>

<h2 id="mission-statement">Mission Statement</h2>

<p>To create a user-friendly map builder that allows anyone to design a visually stunning map in under 15 minutes.</p>

<h2 id="technology-stack">Technology Stack</h2>

<p>To provide a seamless user experience and ensure optimal performance, we utilized a robust tech stack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Supabase</li>
  <li>NextJS</li>
  <li>React</li>
  <li>React Redux</li>
  <li>PixiJS [Extended]</li>
  <li>Tailwind CSS</li>
  <li>Vercel</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="development-history">Development History</h2>

<p>After a constructive 6-month beta period with 700 avid users, our compact team of two initiated a complete overhaul of our map builder, basing every change and improvement on valuable user feedback. Less than 5% of the original codebase was retained, marking a significant evolution of TileForge. We started development of this improved version in early January 2023, culminating in a public launch in May 2023.</p>

<p>During this development phase, I spearheaded 95% of the tasks, which included:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Seamlessly migrating the database from Firebase to Supabase.</li>
  <li>Upgrading PixiJS to v7 for enhanced graphics.</li>
  <li>Reworking all collision logic for wall and floor textures to optimize map integrity.</li>
  <li>Redesigning UI/UX for a smoother, intuitive user experience.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="roles-and-responsibilities">Roles and Responsibilities</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Led UI/UX Design</strong>: Created an intuitive and user-friendly design to enhance the product experience.</li>
  <li><strong>Conducted Customer Discovery</strong>: Engaged in 1:1 interviews and distributed surveys to gather user feedback and needs, thereby shaping our product direction.</li>
  <li><strong>Database Design</strong>: Structured and optimized the database for maximum efficiency and data integrity.</li>
  <li><strong>Managed Project</strong>: Created and managed tasks and sprints, ensuring the timely delivery of features and updates.</li>
  <li><strong>Developed Core Features</strong>: Worked on pivotal feature development to enhance user experience and product usability.</li>
  <li><strong>Created Core Art Assets</strong>: Designed visually appealing art assets to elevate the aesthetic appeal of our tool.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p><strong>Dynamic Lighting:</strong> Dynamic lighting allows users to create lights (e.g. candle) that do not penetrate walls. Combined with color filters, these lights allow for a more emmersive map.</p>

<p><strong>Wall Intersections:</strong> When testing our competitor’s tools, the wall tool was where things would break in stress testing. We managed to build a robust wall tool that can handle everything the average use would throw at it.</p>

<p><strong>Stair Tool:</strong> In our original version of the builder, placing stairs was a challenge. Even though you could see the map layer below as you placed the second story staircase, you often had them misaligned. The stair tool solves this issue by automatically placing stairs above/below the active staircase.</p>

<p><strong>Portal Tool:</strong> The most math intensive tool, portals can be placed along any valid wall and will automatically remove/add the wall beneath upon placing and deleting. The tool adapts to the portal size so that the art assets are not restricted like some tools.</p>

<h2 id="future-developments">Future Developments</h2>

<p>We’re constantly striving to innovate and enhance the capabilities of TileForge. Our current endeavor is the integration of an AI-driven dungeon generator and room decorator. This feature will further simplify map creation and enable users to create good-looking maps in significantly less time. By continuing to listen to our community and refine our tool, we aim to remain at the forefront of virtual map creation for tabletop role-playing games.</p>

<h2 id="elaborated-challenges--solutions">Elaborated Challenges &amp; Solutions</h2>

<h3 id="challenge-1-wall-corners--the-janky-conundrum">Challenge 1: Wall Corners – The Janky Conundrum</h3>

<p>One of the most prominent challenges in 2D graphics engines is texture/UV mapping, particularly around corners. After several attempts and iterations with this approach, we found the results to be far from ideal – let’s just say it was rather “janky”.</p>

<p>The primary issue was rendering wall textures that didn’t necessitate a low-resolution image being stretched, sliced, or rotated to fill the triangles created by the UV mapping around corners. We knew we needed a different approach.</p>

<h4 id="solution-1-masking">Solution 1: Masking</h4>

<p>To combat this, we shifted our strategy from mapping textures to employing masking techniques. Instead of wrapping a texture around the corner based on a single set of points (one line), we would offset the lines to both sides and create two polygons (or one polygon in the case of open loops). One polygon would represent the outer perimeter,</p>

<p>while the other would form the hole in the center. Once the texture was drawn and masked, the black outline was added using the polygons.</p>

<p>This alternative method allowed us to develop tiling wall textures that remained consistent and free from distortion, as the masks would only reveal the texture where the wall was intended to be.</p>

<h3 id="challenge-2-wall-intersections">Challenge 2: Wall Intersections</h3>

<p>While our inventive masking technique solved the issue with wall corners, it also amplified the intricacy of wall intersections.</p>

<p>Initially, walls were drawn as separate objects in a PIXI container that could be individually deleted. If a wall was drawn atop another, it simply appeared above it. However, with the masking technique, all textures were flattened to a single texture layer masked using polygon data. Individual walls were no longer identifiable, as all the polygons had to be reduced down based on their intersections. This posed a significant problem: there’s a myriad of possible combinations for overlapping polygon intersections, each requiring isolation, condition writing, and testing.</p>

<h4 id="solution-2-whiteboard-sessions--persistence">Solution 2: Whiteboard Sessions + Persistence</h4>

<p>Our approach to this was exhaustive but effective: a multitude of whiteboard sessions dedicated to identifying every possible intersection condition and illustrating them. For example, a polygon could overlap the perimeter of another, or a polygon could be inside another but not touch the perimeter.</p>

<p>The complexity grew when considering PixiJS does not permit drawing holes within holes, a scenario that frequently occurs when designing large building layouts. To solve this, we developed a tracking system for parent-child relationships during boolean functions, ensuring the correct assignment of holes to their parent polygons at the end of the sequence.</p>

<p>For each intersection case, we determined what boolean functions needed to be applied and constructed a stack that processed through each existing polygon on the map sequentially. As new polygons were created from boolean functions (e.g., a new hole was formed), they were added to the stack and processed in the correct order. This stack was vital to avoid any out-of-sequence holes or polygons that would result in incorrect parent-child relationships when the final polygons were rendered by PixiJS.</p>

<h3 id="challenge-3-image-transfer-costs--data-overhead">Challenge 3: Image Transfer Costs – Data Overhead</h3>

<p>TileForge, being a web-based application, doesn’t have the benefit of storing art assets locally like some competitors do. This means that each time a user logs in, all art textures need to be requested from the database and loaded into the app, which could lead to significant data transfer costs (~10-15mb of assets each login) when operating at scale.</p>

<h4 id="solution-3-local-caching">Solution 3: Local Caching</h4>

<p>We employed browser caching to locally store the images temporarily in the user’s local storage. When a user logs in, the app checks if the assets already exist and loads them in if necessary. If new or updated assets are detected, the app reloads those assets to ensure the user always has the most current versions of the art. This strategy effectively mitigates high data transfer costs while maintaining a smooth and up-to-date user experience.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jessy Leight Gervais</name><email>jl@copykit.io</email></author><category term="React" /><category term="NextJS" /><category term="TypeScript" /><category term="PixiJS" /><category term="Supabase" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A free to use, web based map builder for tabletop roleplaying gamers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">OttoPlot</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/ottoplot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OttoPlot" /><published>2023-06-28T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-06-28T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/ottoplot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/ottoplot/"><![CDATA[<p>OttoPlot is a creative, generative art project conceived to push the boundaries of my software development skills. Employing a pen plotting machine, Python, and Houdini (Python + VEX), the system processes 3D models into 2D representations and translates them into GCode - the language that CNC machines utilize. This GCode is subsequently transferred to the pen plotter, which diligently sketches the designs onto paper.</p>

<h2 id="background">Background</h2>

<p>OttoPlot emerged from the desire to go beyond the typical web-app development work I was doing from 9-5 and explore generative art. This was an opportunity to revisit fundamental math and challenge myself to learn a new language (VEX).</p>

<h3 id="mission-statement">Mission Statement</h3>

<p>To create generative art through creative programming, thereby transforming 3D models into unique 2D representations.</p>

<h2 id="technology-stack">Technology Stack</h2>

<p>To ensure the flawless execution of this intricate process, a robust and specialized tech stack was utilized:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Python</li>
  <li>Houdini</li>
  <li>Python (with VEX in Houdini)</li>
  <li>Pen Plotting Machine</li>
  <li>GCode</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="project-journey">Project Journey</h2>

<p>OttoPlot’s journey began with curiousity and exploration, during which I revisited basic geometry, algorithm design, and learned about GCode generation. This learning phase was instrumental in shaping the trajectory of the project and in setting a solid foundation for the development work ahead.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Developing Python scripts to process 3D models into 2D representations.</li>
  <li>Learning and implementing VEX scripting in Houdini for advanced 3D model manipulation.</li>
  <li>Parsing 2D representations into GCode.</li>
  <li>Managing and calibrating the pen plotting machine to ensure accurate output.</li>
  <li>Refining the algorithm to optimize the aesthetic appeal of the final designs.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="roles-and-responsibilities">Roles and Responsibilities</h2>

<p><strong>Mathematical Modeling</strong>: Developed and implemented complex geometrical and algorithmic models.
<strong>Software Development</strong>: Designed and wrote Python scripts for model processing and GCode generation.
<strong>Machine Operation</strong>: Managed the pen plotting machine, ensuring its calibration and correct operation.
<strong>Aesthetic Refinement</strong>: Iteratively improved the algorithm to optimize the aesthetic appeal of the final designs.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jessy Leight Gervais</name><email>jl@copykit.io</email></author><category term="Python" /><category term="VEX" /><category term="Houdini" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A generative AI project using Python, VEX, and GCode to process 3D objects into vector shapes and drawn with pen plotting machine.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Protogen</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/protogen/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Protogen" /><published>2023-06-27T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-06-27T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/protogen</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/protogen/"><![CDATA[<p>Protogen is an internal project built to streamline our team’s capability in rapidly prototyping custom solutions for our clients. Specifically designed for use in manufacturing facilities, we aimed to customize software to cater to a diverse range of use cases put forth by our clients. However, we frequently faced capacity constraints due to the considerable time invested in constructing these custom solutions over our existing software base.</p>

<h2 id="background">Background</h2>

<p>Working hand in hand with our CTO, we developed a no-code platform during after-hours for internal use. Protogen’s solution transformed AirTable relational tables into an SQL database, which was further leveraged by a series of scripts to construct the necessary forms and pages using Django and NextJS. By implementing standardized forms and CRUD operations, our team could transition from an AirTable prototype to a fully deployed MVP on Vercel in less than 10 minutes.</p>

<p>Though an internal project, a similar application named Stacker was developed and launched publicly around the same period. Our unique implementation was better suited to our company’s needs. By transitioning to SQL, we were not confined by the delay in response times when updating/requesting records via AirTable’s API, which at the time stood between 5 to 10 minutes.</p>

<h2 id="mission-statement">Mission Statement</h2>

<p>Our mission statement: To design a tool that enables rapid prototyping of custom solutions, taking our team from an AirTable prototype to a deployed MVP in under 10 minutes.</p>

<h2 id="technology-stack">Technology Stack</h2>

<ul>
  <li>SQL (Transferred from AirTable)</li>
  <li>Django</li>
  <li>NextJS</li>
  <li>React</li>
  <li>Tailwind CSS</li>
  <li>DigitalOcean</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="key-responsibilities">Key Responsibilities</h2>

<p>During the project, my key responsibilities included:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>UI/UX Design</strong>: I designed a user-friendly and intuitive interface to optimize the product experience.</li>
  <li><strong>Database Design</strong>: I structured and optimized the SQL database for maximum efficiency and data integrity.</li>
  <li><strong>Product Design</strong>: I played a pivotal role in conceptualizing and designing Protogen to address our company’s unique needs.</li>
  <li><strong>Project Management</strong>: I was in charge of creating and managing tasks and sprints, ensuring timely delivery of updates and features.</li>
  <li><strong>Co-development of Core Features</strong>: I collaborated directly with the CTO to develop essential features of Protogen via Live Share (5-6 months)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Protogen serves as a testament to our team’s determination and ability to solve internal bottlenecks, providing an efficient solution to quickly prototype and deploy custom applications for our clients. The success of Protogen is reflected in the significant reduction of our team’s time spent on building custom solutions, paving the way for more effective use of resources.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jessy Leight Gervais</name><email>jl@copykit.io</email></author><category term="React" /><category term="TypeScript" /><category term="Django" /><category term="SQL" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An internal no-code prototype library that translates AirTable relational tables into SQL + Django with pre-built front-end/CRUD.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TileForge Website</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/tileforge-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TileForge Website" /><published>2023-06-25T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-06-25T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/tileforge-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/tileforge-website/"><![CDATA[<p>After the public launch of the TileForge builder, we needed a website that could capture leads and nurture prospective customers into converted users. We knew we were going to rely heavily on content marketing, so integrating email sign ups and a blog was important. The website would not only function as an informational hub about the product but also hosts an engaging blog and facilitates user registration.</p>

<p>You can view the active website at: <a href="https://tileforge.com">www.tileforge.com</a></p>

<h2 id="objective">Objective</h2>

<p>Our aim was ambitious yet straightforward: to develop an engaging, informative platform that would not only act as a gateway to our map builder but also significantly enhance our content marketing efforts. A crucial part of our strategy was the inclusion of a blog and email sign-ups, which would help in both attracting and nurturing leads. Building on this foundation, we devised TileForge Website, which has since played a pivotal role in converting prospects into active users, with a customer base that continues to grow steadily.</p>

<h2 id="mission-statement">Mission Statement</h2>

<p>To create an attractive, high converting website for the TileForge project.</p>

<h2 id="technology-stack">Technology Stack</h2>

<p>To ensure a superior user experience and peak performance, we employed a robust tech stack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Contentful</li>
  <li>NextJS</li>
  <li>React</li>
  <li>React Redux</li>
  <li>Tailwind CSS</li>
  <li>Vercel</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="project-development">Project Development</h2>

<p>Following the public launch of the TileForge builder, our team dedicated itself to developing a complementary website that would aid in lead generation and user conversion. The project started in May 2023, shortly after the builder’s launch, and culminated in a successful public release in September 2023. My role during this period was extensive and included:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Establishing the Contentful database to manage website content efficiently.</li>
  <li>Integrating an engaging blog section to bolster content marketing efforts.</li>
  <li>Incorporating an email sign-up feature to capture and nurture leads.</li>
  <li>Streamlining UI/UX for a smooth and user-friendly browsing experience.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="roles-and-responsibilities">Roles and Responsibilities</h2>

<p><strong>Led UI/UX Design</strong>: Devised a user-friendly and intuitive design to boost the browsing experience.
<strong>Managed Content</strong>: Oversaw the curation and presentation of engaging and informative content to attract and nurture leads.
<strong>Database Design</strong>: Structured and optimized the Contentful database to manage website content effectively.
<strong>Managed Project</strong>: Coordinated and oversaw tasks and milestones, ensuring timely delivery of features and updates.
<strong>Developed Core Features</strong>: Played a key role in feature development, such as blog integration and email sign-ups, to enhance user engagement and lead conversion.
<strong>Executed Marketing Strategies</strong>: Effectively leveraged content marketing and lead nurturing strategies to convert prospects into active users.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jessy Leight Gervais</name><email>jl@copykit.io</email></author><category term="NextJS" /><category term="React" /><category term="React Redux" /><category term="Contentful" /><category term="TailwindCSS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A marketing website for the TileForge project, including a blog.]]></summary></entry></feed>